Guide to the Hyman Steinberg Collection on Solar Research MC.285
New York University Archives
Hyman Steinberg Collection on Solar Research
1952-2005
New York University Archives
Steinberg, Hyman
MC.285
.75 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 film can
1 16mm_film_reels
Hyman Steinberg (1925-2016) was a teacher, scientist, and engineer who held over 20 patents for various inventions, including solar technology innovations, hearing aids, and rotary shavers. He worked in the fields of architecture, engineering, public relations, and consulting, and held positions at New York University (1951-1955) and the John F. Kennedy Space Center (1967-1971). This collection consists of materials created and collected by Steinberg in the 1950s and 1960s documenting his research in solar power and the development, production, and promotion of the Sundiner Solar Cooking Oven (also referred to as a grill in some materials). Materials in this collection include engineering drawings; domestic and international patents; press releases; advertisements; reports for potential investors; photographic negatives, prints, and slides used to demonstrate or promote the grill; and correspondence concerning the business aspects of the invention process, including production and manufacturing costs. Materials also include one 16mm film reel from 1953 demonstrating home construction techniques based on Steinberg's research.
Scope and Contents
This collection consists of materials created and collected by Hyman Steinberg in the 1950s and 1960s documenting his research in solar power and the development, production, and promotion of the Sundiner Solar Cooking Oven (also referred to as the Sunpower Solar Grill in some materials). Materials in this collection include engineering drawings; domestic and international patents; press releases; advertisements; reports for potential investors; photographic negatives, prints, and slides used to demonstrate or promote the oven; and correspondence concerning the business aspects of the invention process, including production and manufacturing costs. Materials also include one 16mm film reel from 1953 demonstrating home construction techniques based on Steinberg's research. The collection includes reports and research not related to solar energy, such as a plan for a laboratory facility.
Arrangement
This collection has not been arranged by an archivist. The materials are arranged in the order in which they were received from the donor.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by David Steinberg, Hyman Steinberg's son, in December 2017 and February 2018; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2018.003 and 2018.009, respectively. David Steinberg donated an accretion consisting of one film reel in January 2025; the accession number associated with this gift is 2025.002.
Biographical Note
Hyman Steinberg (1925-2016) was a teacher, scientist, and engineer who held over 20 patents for various inventions, including solar technology innovations, hearing aids, and rotary shavers. Steinberg served as a Radioman in the United States Navy from 1944-1946, after which he earned his Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Engineering (1951) from Oklahoma State University. He worked in the fields of architecture, engineering, public relations, and consulting, and held specialist positions at New York University (1951-1955) and the John F. Kennedy Space Center (1967-1971). A major avenue of Steinberg's innovation focused on applications of solar energy and the development of his invention, the Sundiner Solar Energy Grill.
Source:
Dignity Memorial. "Hyman Steinberg Obituary." Dignitymemorial.com. http://obits.dignitymemorial.com/dignity-memorial/obituary.aspx?n=Hyman-Steinberg&lc=7083&pid=177719394&mid=6801159 (retrieved February 15, 2018).
Appraisal
In March 2019, one of the solar grills in this collection was deaccessioned and transferred to the New York University Poly Archives and Special Collections.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact New York University Archives, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Solar energy; Engineering; Solar collectors; Patents; Inventions; Technical drawings
- Brochures, Engineering Drawings, Research, 1952-1960s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- "The Solar Cooking Oven" Report for the Ford Foundation by Maria Telkes, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence and Advertising, 1962-1971 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Photographs, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
- International Patents, 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- "Temperature Protection of Packages," Maria Telkes and Hyman Steinberg, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Photographs of Early Prototypes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Architectural Drawing: "Foundation and Heating", 1952 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Living with Energy, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Proceedings of the World Symposium on Applied Solar Energy, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Construction Research, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Sheathing Materials and Methods, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Sunpower Solar Grill Brochure, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Department of Public Works Identification Card and Photograph, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- United States Patents, 1962-1984 (Box 1, Folder 15, Box 2, Folder 1-2)
- International Patents (Front Covers), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- List of Patents, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Sketch of High Temperature Creep Test Facility, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- "New Laboratory for Trapping the Sun's Bounty," Engineering Scientist, 1951-1955 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Clippings, correspondence, article, photos (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Sunpower Solar Grill, ca. 1972; MC.285.cuid3656 (Object Solar Oven 2, Object Solar Oven 1)
- Home Construction Techniques Film, 1953; cuid18767 (Film canister cuid18767)